Finding Aid for Provost and Executive Vice-President for Academic Affairs (University of Michigan) Supplemental Files, 1952-[ongoing]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Provost and Executive Vice-President for Academic Affairs (University of Michigan) Supplemental Files 1953-[ongoing]
University of Michigan. Provost and Executive Vice-President for Academic Affairs.
59 linear feet
87365 Bimu B6 2
Central academic administrative unit of the University of Michigan which functions as chief executive assistant to the president, responsible for appointments and promotions with oversight for schools, colleges, educational units and programs; including budget planning, legislative relations, institutional research, and affirmative action policies. Supplemental Files subgroup includes material on a number of subjects that was filed separately from the vice presidents' or staff's papers when the record group was received.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Provost's Office (Donor no. 5120) makes periodic additions to the records. Records were first received in 1971. NO.
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted in order to protect individual privacy. Certain administrative records are restricted in accordance with university policy as outlined below. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws, including the Freedom of Information Act.
The Supplemental Files subgroup of the record group University of Michigan Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 19-41, 47-50
Student Educational Records -- Box 19
Executive Officers Records -- Boxes 43, 45-46, 50-59
As of 1995 the office represented by this record group is officially titled the Office of the Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs. Previous titles of the office were: Vice Presidents for Academic Affairs and Provost, 1983-1995; Vice President for Academic Affairs, 1962-1983; and Provost, 1938-1962.
Provost
The origins of this office date back to 1938, during President Ruthven's administration, when the position of provost was created by a bylaw of the Board of Regents to "aid the President by performing such of the President's functions as shall from time to time be delegated by him or by the Board of Regents" (Regents' Proceedings, March 1938, p. 505). E. Blythe Stason, the dean of the Law School who had already been performing many of these functions, was appointed the first provost. Stason resigned as provost in November 1944 to devote his attentions to the leadership of the Law School, and James P. Adams, vice president of Brown University and former University of Michigan economics professor, assumed the post of provost and professor of economics in January 1945. At the Regents' meeting of January 1945 the bylaw establishing the provost's position was amended to include the statement that the provost "shall be the chief executive officer of the University next to the President" (Regents' Bylaw 2.02). Adams remained the provost until his resignation in July 1951. A successor to Adams was not named, and the responsibilities of the provost were absorbed by the newly created vice president and dean of faculties, Marvin Niehuss.
Vice President for Academic Affairs
In 1962 two new positions were created in the university administration: executive vice president and vice president for academic affairs.
Marvin Niehuss, vice president for university relations since 1945 and the vice president and dean of faculties since 1951, was promoted to the position of executive vice president in 1962. As vice president and dean of faculties, Niehuss had coordinated university relations with the state legislature and had overseen the administration of the schools, colleges, and other units (including institutes, Extension Service, summer session, and the Reserve Officers' Training Corps), reporting on enrollment, teaching loads, research, and faculty salaries. In his new position as executive vice president, Niehuss continued to supervise legislative relations and served as the University's contact with the state board of education. In addition, the executive vice president was the chief executive assistant to the president and assumed the duties and powers of the president in his absence. (When Niehuss retired in 1968 the position of executive vice president was abolished and a vice president for state relations and planning was established in its place.)
Roger Heyns, a member of the Psychology Department and since 1959 dean of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, was appointed to the position of vice president for academic affairs in 1962. Heyns assumed many of the duties previously performed by the vice president and dean of faculties. He was given general executive responsibility for the faculty and for the academic programs of the schools, colleges, and other educational units. He reviewed recommendations of deans, directors, and department heads with regard to appointments, promotions, leaves of absence, and salaries of faculty members and special service personnel. In addition, the Offices of Admissions, and Registration and Records--previously under the jurisdiction of the vice president for student affairs--were brought under the vice president for academic affairs.
This reorganization of administrative responsibilities was intended as a means of unifying planning in a period of rapid growth of the University. In actual practice, the duties associated with planning remained dispersed and were shifted from one office to another in the 1960s and 1970s. When a vice presidency for state relations and planning was established in 1968, some of the responsibility for academic program planning was transferred to that office. The Office of Institutional Research, which collected and analyzed data on enrollment trends, faculty characteristics, funding, and related subjects, was transferred in 1969 from Academic Affairs to State Relations and Planning. In 1974 the Office of Institutional Research was renamed the Office of Academic Planning and Analysis and was returned to Academic Affairs, reflecting the assignment of additional evaluation and planning responsibilities under the vice president for academic affairs. Over the course of the 1960s and 1970s, the vice president for academic affairs gradually assumed greater responsibility for budget preparation.
In addition to program and budget planning, the Office of Academic Affairs was involved in implementing affirmative action plans, overseeing the Opportunity Program and Tuskegee-Michigan exchange program, and coordinating support services for minority students.
When Roger Heyns left the university in 1965 to become chancellor of the University of California at Berkeley, he was succeeded by Allan F. Smith, the dean of the Law School. Smith held the post of vice president for academic affairs for nine years and in 1974 was followed by Frank H. T. Rhodes, a professor of geology and since 1971 dean of the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts. Rhodes resigned in 1977 to assume the presidency of Cornell University.
Harold T. Shapiro, chairman of the Economics Department, was appointed vice president for academic affairs in 1977 and held the position until 1980, when he became president of the University of Michigan. Alfred Sussman, dean of Rackham School of Graduate Studies, served as acting vice president for academic affairs from November 1, 1979 through July 1, 1980, when Billy E. Frye, professor of Zoology and dean of the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts, assumed the position.
Vice President for Academic Affairs and Provost
At its February 1983 meeting, the Regents of the University of Michigan changed the title of the position to Vice President for Academic Affairs and Provost (hereafter referred to as "provost"). The move to include "provost" in the title was taken in part because of the increased responsibility of the vice president within the university's administration and because of the need to assist the president as he moved into state and national projects, notably the management of the capital campaign fund-raising effort.
In 1986, Billy E. Frye resigned and was replaced by James J. Duderstadt, dean of the College of Engineering, who served as provost until he became the president of the university in September 1988. Robert Holbrook served as interim provost until December 1988. In January 1989, Charles Vest, dean of the College of Engineering, became provost and remained until July 1990, when he left to assume the presidency of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Holbrook served as interim provost for the month of August, after which Gilbert Whitaker, dean of the School of Business Administration, began his tenure as provost.
Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs
In September 1993 the Regents approved a change in title to provost and executive vice president for academic affairs. This title was intended to reflect more accurately the responsibilities of the provost and to "bring Michigan into line with the administrative structures of other universities" (The University Record 49(3), 1993 September 20: 4). The new designation came about when President Duderstadt recommended a change in title for Whitaker. In 1995 Whitaker returned to teaching and was succeeded by J. Bernard Machen, dean of the School of Dentistry. Machen initially served on an interim basis before agreeing to accept a two-year appointment. He did not seek an extension and was succeeded by Nancy Cantor, dean of the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies in 1997.
The position vice provost for academic affairs was created in 1990 to recognize university-wide activities in which John H. D'Arms, dean of Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies, was engaged that were beyond the scope of his decanal responsibilities. Such responsibilities included overseeing the Bentley Historical Library and the Clements Library, evaluating promotion and tenure dossiers, and serving as liaison between the university and major foundations (The University Record 45(24), 1990 March 26: 1). With the appointment of new provosts the functional responsibilities and reporting relationships of the vice provost have frequently changed.
Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs
1993-1995 Gilbert R. Whitaker, Jr.
1996 J. Bernard Machen (interim)
1996-1997 J. Bernard Machen
1997- Nancy Cantor
Vice Presidents for Academic Affairs and Provost
1962-1965 Roger W. Heyns
1965-1974 Allen F. Smith
1974-1977 Frank H.T. Rhodes
1977-1979 Harold T. Shapiro
1979-1980 Alfred S. Sussman (Interim)
1980-1986 Billy E. Frye
1986-1988 James J. Duderstadt
1988 Robert S. Holbrook (Interim)
1989-1990 Charles M. Vest
1990 Robert S. Holbrook (Interim)
1990-1993 Gilbert R. Whitaker, Jr.
Vice Provost for Academic Affairs
1990-1995 John H. D'Arms
Associate Provosts
1993-1997 Robert Holbrook
1993-1997 Susan Lipschutz
Associate Vice Presidents
1971-1975 John Romani
1974-1981 Richard English
1975-1981 Carolyne K. Davis
1981-1993 Robert S. Holbrook
1981-1983 W. Allen Spivey
1983-1993 Mary Ann Swain
1988- John H. Jackson
Administrative Deans
1962-1974 Robert L. Williams
Assistant Vice Presidents
1974/75-1981/82 Edward A. Dougherty
1965-1981/82 Ernest R. Zimmermann
1983- Robert B. Holmes
1984-1986 Niara Sudarkasa
1983-1988 Robin Jacoby
1989- E. Kay Dawson
Summary Contents List
Alliance for Undergraduate Education -- Box 44
Awards -- Box 7
Black Action Movement (BAM) -- Box 2
Budget Priorities Committee (BPC) -- Boxes 7-9
Career Development Fund for Women Faculty -- Boxes 47-50
Child Care Task Force (1996-1998) -- Box 46
Dean and Director Reviews -- Box 21
Ford Foundation Grants -- Boxes 2-3
Graduate Employees Organization (GEO) -- Boxes 3-5
Higher Education General Information Survey -- Box 10
Historical Files -- Box 5
Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disabilities (ISMRRD) -- Box 5
Management Advisory Group: Professional and Advisory Salary Implementation Program -- Box 6
Minority Affairs Quality of Student Life Survey -- Box 42
Office Policy and Office Holder Documents -- Boxes 43, 50
Opportunity Program -- Box 1
Presidents' Council of the State Universities of Michigan (PCSUM) -- Boxes 51-59
Proposals -- Boxes 11-12
Reports -- Boxes 13-14
Residential College -- Box 6
Reviews -- Boxes 15-18
Searches -- Boxes 22-41
Senate Advisory Committee on Staff Excellence -- Box 6
State Plan for Higher Education -- Box 18
State Postsecondary Review Entities (SPRES) -- Box 18
Task Force on Campus Safety and Security (1997) -- Box 45
Thurnau Trust and Thurnau Professorships -- Boxes 46-47
The Supplemental Files subgroup of the record group Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs consists of 59 linear feet and spans the years from 1953 to 1995. This subgroup consists of material that was not interfiled with the vice presidents' or staff's papers when the record group was received. The records generally were not created or maintained by any one staff member in the Office of Academic Affairs, but rather are the result of the examination of a particular issue or topic over a period of time by a variety of people.
There are twenty-seven series of varying sizes which comprise this subgroup. For an alphabetical list of the series in this subgroup, please consult the summary contents list on pages viii and ix of this section.
Subjects:
Afro-Americans--Michigan.; American Council on Education.; Black Action Movement (University of Michigan); Committee on Institutional Cooperation.; Ford Foundation.; Grand Rapids University Consortium Center.; Graduate Employees Organization (University of Michigan); Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies.; Michigan. Dept. of Education.; Michigan. Legislature.; Michigan. State Board of Education.; Draft--Michigan.; Tuskegee Institute.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities.; United States. Selective Service System.; United States. Army. Reserve Officers' Training Corps.; Universities and colleges--United States.; University of Michigan--Accreditation.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan--Awards.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan. Budget Priorities Committee.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Design.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Urban Planning.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science, and the Arts.; University of Michigan. College of Pharmacy.; University of Michigan--Congresses.; University of Michigan--Dearborn.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Geography.; University of Michigan. Division of the Health Sciences.; University of Michigan. Evaluation and Planning Project.; University of Michigan. Extension Service.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Finance.; University of Michigan--Flint.; University of Michigan--Grants.; University of Michigan. Information Technology Division.; University of Michigan. Institute for Human Adjustment.; University of Michigan. Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disabilities.; University of Michigan. Institute of Public Policy Studies.; University of Michigan. Institute of Gerontology.; University of Michigan--Law School.; University of Michigan. Library.; University of Michigan. Medical Center.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan--Students.; University of Michigan. Museum of Art.; University of Michigan. Opportunity Program.; University of Michigan--Planning.; University of Michigan--Research.; University of Michigan. Residential College.; University of Michigan--Students--Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; University of Michigan. School of Art.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.; University of Michigan. School of Education.; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration.; University of Michigan. School of Information and Library Studies.; University of Michigan. School of Music.; University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.; University of Michigan. School of Social Work.; University of Michigan. Senate.; University of Michigan--Students--Political activity.; University Center for Adult Education (Wayne State University-University of Michigan-Eastern Michigan University); University of Michigan. University Hospital.; University of Michigan. Vice-President and Chief Financial Officer.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Academic Affairs.; Demonstrations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Minority college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Provost and Executive Vice-President for Academic Affairs.
Contributors:
Cash, William L.; Davis, Carolyne K.; Dougherty, Edward A.; Duderstadt, James J., 1942-; English, Richard A.; Frye, B. E. (Billy Eugene); Goodman, George.; Heyns, Roger W. (Roger William), 1918-1995; Holbrook, Robert S.; Holmes, Robert Bradford.; Rhodes, Frank Harold Trevor.; Romani, John Henry, 1925-; Shapiro, Harold T., 1935-; Smith, Allan Frederick, 1911-; Spurr, Stephen Hopkins.; Sudarkasa, Niara.; Sussman, Alfred S.; Swain, Mary Ann Price, 1941-; Williams, Robert Lewis, 1903-; Zimmermann, Ernest R.
- Supplemental Files
  - Opportunity Program 1967-1980
    The Opportunity Program series, 1967-1980 (1 lin. ft.), consists mainly of papers of George D. Goodman, who became director of the program in 1973/74 and had been on the staff prior to that time. The Opportunity Program was created in 1963/64 to provide scholarships and support services for disadvantaged, primarily minority, students. Goodman's papers, which are arranged alphabetically by subject, include information on minority recruitment, enrollment, and support services, as well as minutes of Opportunity Program staff meetings. There is also a small quantity of papers of William L. Cash, Jr., who as assistant to the president for human relations affairs coordinated the program in 1971/72. Researchers should also see subseries on the Opportunity Program in the files of Richard English and John Romani in the Staff Files subgroup.
    - Equal Opportunity Report 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - Cash, William L., Jr. Files
      - General 1968-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Minority Student Support Services 1972 (Box 1)
      - Staff Support Applications 1972 (Box 1)
    - Goodman, George Files
      - Bakke Case (Box 1)
      - Black History Month 1980 (Box 1)
      - Detroit Orientation 1980 (Box 1)
      - English Composition Board (ECB) Conference Proceedings 1978 (Box 1)
      - Media: Lou Gordon Program 1973 (Box 1)
      - Minority Enrollment Report 1973-1979, 7 folders (Box 1)
      - Minority Enrollment Survey, Fall 1970 (Box 1)
      - Minority Pre-Orientation Program March 1980 (Box 1)
      - Minority Recruitment and Admissions 1973 (Box 1)
      - Minority Student Services: Professional Schools 1973 (Box 1)
      - Post-Graduation Job Histories of Opportunity Award (Box 1)
      - Students (Luke Tripp Research) 1977 (Box 1)
      - Recruitment and Retention of Undergraduate Minority Students (Box 1)
      - Staff Meetings 1978-1980 (Box 1)
      - Staff Planning 1980 (Box 1)
      - Support Services: Reading and Learning Skills Center 1978 (Box 1)
      - Tenth Anniversary Celebration 1974 (Box 1)
      - Tutorial Program Plan (Box 1)
  - Black Action Movement (BAM) 1967-1975
    The Black Action Movement (BAM) series, 1967-1975 (0.7 lin. ft.) mainly documents the activities of BAM from its organization in 1969 to 1971, including the university administration's reaction to the campus-wide strike of 1970. Some earlier material offers background on the campus climate for black students.
    - General 1969-1970, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Afro-American Studies 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Afro-American and African Studies, Center for (CAAS) 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Appeal Procedures 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Black Enrollment (quotas) 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Black Student Center 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Black Student Program 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Black Student Supportive Services 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Complaints regarding BAM 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Demands 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Disciplinary Actions 1969-1971 (Box 19)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2046 ]
    - Disciplinary Procedures 1969-1971, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Discipline
      - General 1969-1970 (Box 2)
      - Strikes 1969-1971, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Disruptions 1967-1971, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Faculty Reactions 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Negro History Course (LSA) 1967-1968 (Box 2)
    - Recruitment 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Rhodes, Frank (Provost) 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - Tarrant, Shawn (Asst. Director of University Housing) 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - University Statements 1969-1971, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Ford Foundation Grants 1959-1968, 1.1 linear foot
    The Ford Foundation Grants series, 1959-1968 (1.1 lin. ft.) is divided into two subseries, Area and International Studies, and Population Program. The records document the university's use of two grants given by the Ford Foundation in 1961 and 1966 totaling 7.5 million dollars for teaching and research on the non-Western world. These grants made possible the establishment of various centers on campus, such as the Center for Population Planning.
    - Area and International Studies 1959-1967
      - Accounting 1965-1967 (Box 2)
      - Budget Requests 1961-1966 (Box 2)
      - Committees
        - Area Studies Liaison 1959-1964 (Box 2)
        - International Programs Faculty Advisory Committee 1966-1968 (Box 2)
        - Joint Area and International Studies Committee 1964-1965 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1963-1967, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Council on International Programs 1966-1968, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Development Funds 1962-1967 (1 of 3 folders) (Box 2)
      - Development Funds 1962-1967 (2 of 3 folders) (Box 3)
      - Important Documents 1961-1966 (Box 3)
      - Programs
        - 5-year 1961-1966 (Box 3)
        - 10-year 1961-1962 (Box 3)
      - Proposals
        - 1961-1962 (Box 3)
        - 1966-1967 (Box 3)
      - Reports 1963-1966 (Box 3)
    - Population Program 1964-1968
      - General 1964-1965, 1967-1968, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Accounting and Budgets 1966-1967 (Box 3)
      - Centers
        - Population Planning 1965-1968 (Box 3)
        - Population Studies 1963-1967 (Box 3)
        - Research in Reproductive Biology 1965-1967 (Box 3)
      - Committees 1965-1967 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1965-1968 (Box 3)
      - Development Fund 1966-1967 (Box 3)
      - Proposals for Grant Extension
        - Center for Population Planning June 1967 (Box 3)
        - Center for Research in Reproductive Biology 1967, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Reports 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Graduate Employees Organization (GEO) 1974-1977, 1.4 linear foot
    The series of records regarding the Graduate Employees Organization (GEO) (1.4 linear ft) dates from the union's organization in 1974 to 1977, including the five-week strike in March 1975. Material relates to affirmative action and negotiations between GEO and the university.
    - General, 11 folders
      - 1974-1977, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - 1974-1977, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Advisory Committee 1974-1976, 9 folders (Box 4)
    - Affirmative Action
      - General, 3 folders
        - 1975-1976, 1 folders (Box 4)
        - 1975-1976, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Strike
      - Effects
        - General 1974-1975 (Box 5)